Guide to the Dante Gabriel Rossetti Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 June 1; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.62)
  Rossetti suggests that Heaton and Mrs. Gurney postpone their visit until he is better prepared as he does not have much work to show them. Rossetti says he will have more work, including "your Beatrice," at a more advanced stage later (actually a reference to The Beloved -- see Fredeman). Rossetti tells Heaton he will arrange an appointment for Heaton to meet Mr. Rose when Rose visits Rossetti the following day.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beloved; Rose, James Anderson, 1819-1890; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 July 2; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 2 folded sheets (7 pages): autograph letter signed; each sheet 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.68)
  With envelope. Addressed from 16 Cheyne Walk. Date from Fredeman.
  Rossetti has received word from his Christina Rossetti that Heaton would like a copy of one of the photos Rossetti has recently taken of Ruskin. Rossetti says he will send Heaton one, once they are printed but requests that she keeps it strictly in her possession, as a matter of legality. Rossetti is a little perturbed with Heaton's Beatrice painting, as the model he has employed to sit for the work differs in appearance from Beatrice's described appearance. Rossetti asks if he can change the work's subject to the bride from Solomon's Song, to better fit the model (a work that became The Beloved ). Rossetti invites Heaton to view the completed head of the piece. Rossetti ends: "Hoping letter does not seem alarming as regards the picture, which promise you shall in any case be a thoroughly good specimen of work."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beloved; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 July 4; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.70)
  Rossetti promises Heaton that he has not forgotten her photograph of Ruskin but that he does not have one to send her at present. He tells Heaton Tuesday would be best for her to visit him, and offers a time of 5:30 pm or before 11am. Rossetti says that the Beatrice must be turned into Solomon's Bride and states that he will title the work The King's Daughter (i.e. The Beloved ). Rossetti thinks that Heaton will still want the piece but, if she doesn't, he will paint her a Beatrice when he can find an appropriate model. He thinks Jane Morris would be suitable but that hiring her "would cause loss of time and patience" if indeed she is available. He states that "to paint it from any study, without nature, would be impossible."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beloved; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Morris, Jane, 1839-1914; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 August 1; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 2 folded sheets (7 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.78)
  With envelope. Letterhead: 16 Cheyne Walk.
  Rossetti apologizes for his delayed response; he has been in Brighton for two days. Rossetti admits he sent Heaton's drawing without a case (which had gone missing) and trusted his frame-maker to pack it carefully. Rossetti regrets that he will not have the two additional figures included in his picture by the end of the following week, as he has many earlier deadlines for other works. Rossetti apologizes if this means that Heaton will not be able to view the work before she leaves London but says that he can give her an idea of its arrangement by sending her a pen and ink sketch of what he proposes. The two additional figures would be "2 dark girls harping." Rossetti thinks that decisions regarding the work should be postponed until it is more advanced. In any case, he "might possibly be beginning a Beatrice if a model turned up." Rossetti asks Heaton how she likes his new writing paper (which features Rossetti's crest, monogram and Cheyne Walk address).
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beloved; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 September 26; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.88)
  Rossetti asks Heaton to loan him her drawing of Dante's Dream as he wishes to begin an oil painting on the same subject. He promises he will only ask for it once he is able to start the work immediately and will return it, along with an additional sketch, once the oil work has been started. Rossetti admits that he has not being doing much work with regards to The Beloved and that he will notify Heaton as soon as he does. Rossetti says he visited Belgium with his brother and that the rest of his time has been occupied with water colour reproductions of The salutation of Beatrice. Heaton has been in Newcastle and Rossetti hopes she enjoyed her time there. He regrets that Ruskin's portrait has been published "against his desire and injunction."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beloved; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Salutation of Beatrice; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 October 14; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.92)
  Rossetti admits he still does not know exactly when he will need Dante's Dream but that it is likely he will require it before the end of the month. He says he will write as soon as he knows the exact time. Rossetti is perturbed by Heaton's reports of changes in his drawing and hopes that they are a result of the positioning of the pieces or how Heaton is looking at them. He says the "darkened" white in the St George should be easily and permanently remedied and suggests that Heaton send him the St George alongside the Dante's Dream, so that he might fix it. Rossetti says he has not seen Burne Jones since his return and so cannot know what he thinks about the matter.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 October 25; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.95)
  With envelope. Letter has rectangle measuring 2 x 3.5 cm cut out between the date and salutation -- presumably Rossetti's crest and monograph. Also cut away is a piece measuring 2 x 11.3 cm, for the signature.
  Rossetti expresses his happiness that Heaton's "charming class of critics" like his work and says he is happy to show any of them his studio. Rossetti says he has heard from Ruskin, who is en route to England. Rossetti is making two Dante drawings for Lady Ashburton, jointly titled The salutation of Beatrice, which are similarly composed to works Rossetti showed Heaton in oil. These works are in watercolor. Rossetti describes a piece he is currently working on as depicting "a lady plaiting her golden hair" in oil ( Fazio's mistress ). (Here, a piece of the letter measuring 2 cm x 11.3 cm is cut away.) Rossetti asks Heaton for the Dante's Dream and requests that she send it alongside the St George for alteration. Rossetti compares Heaton's St John to Lady Trevelyan's, saying Heaton's is "more forcible" and Trevelyan's "the more finished."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Mary in the house of St. John; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Salutation of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Fazio's mistress; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 November 11; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.97)
  With envelope. Letterhead: 16 Cheyne Walk. Date from Fredeman.
  Rossetti tells Heaton he will return the Bethlehem Gate piece she has sent to him as he cannot detect "any alteration whatever" in the work. Rossetti similarly finds Dante's dream unchanged but says he knows how he can revise it and greatly improve it. He states he can heighten its colour and removed the "stiffness, smallness of execution" in the work but that it would take a week or a fortnight to change and could only be done as a commission. If Heaton does not wish Rossetti to carry out the alterations, Rossetti states he will not need to keep the drawing long. Rossetti says he will try to photograph the work but he does not expect the endeavor to be "very promising." In a postscript, Rossetti suggests that Heaton has the work's frame and the inscription replaced and asks if he should arrange for this to be carried out.
  Picture frames and framing; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Bethlehem Gate; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 November 21; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.104)
  With envelope. Rossetti's crest and monogram have been cut away.
  Rossetti says he has not made any alterations to Dante's dream except to make Dante's feet smaller, "they being (I know not by what hallucination on my part) of the canoe class in shape and size." Rossetti agrees it is better to remain unchanged. Rossetti has not yet used the picture and asks if Heaton will allow him to keep it a little longer, especially as she intends to "defer its return ... for a much less important object -- namely its loan to Mr. Ruskin." Rossetti will have the frame repaired. Rossetti will send Heaton some samples of his autograph as she asked but admits his delay in doing so is a result of his "real horror of autography."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1863 December 22; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 63.116)
  Rossetti has received an offer for The beloved and asks Heaton if she is no longer interested in the work. He says he has done no further work to the piece but has extended his plans for it so he can no longer paint it for 200 guineas, the price he first named for Heaton. Rossetti asks if he could paint her something else and says he has not forgotten the £50 she has given him for a painting of Beatrice. Rossetti has found a partly completed picture of his wife in oil, begun as a picture of Beatrice, which might possibly be able to be worked into a painting depicting Beatrice falling asleep by a wall and a sundial ( Beata Beatrix ). Rossetti apologizes for keeping the Dante's dream for so long and says he will try to get a photograph of it while he still has it.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beata Beatrix; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beloved; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 April 19; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.51)
  Rossetti tells Heaton that her Dante's dream was taken by Ruskin on the day prior to his father's death, in order for Ruskin to photograph it. He assures her that nothing has been altered in the piece. Rossetti says that he will be glad to see her when she is in London and expresses his approval of Ruskin possibly lecturing in Bradford. Rossetti still has Heaton's Bethlehem Gate and supposes that she will collect it when in London. He asks if he could see the St. George again, to assess whether it has changed colour but believes that Heaton is again mistaken on that point. Rossetti writes: "All autographs of all kinds will be at all times at your service, when not altogether suppressed and abolished."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Bethlehem Gate; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. St. George and the Princess Sabra; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 May 11; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.62)
  Rossetti is having his mother and sister for dinner the following day and hopes Heaton will attend. Rossetti has been so busy that he has not made any changes to Bethlehem Gate but says that if it is not retouched by dinner, it will be by Monday (the 16th). Rossetti expresses his annoyance about the photograph (presumably the one of Dante's dream to be taken by Ruskin). Rossetti tells Heaton that his pencil drawing for her will be framed and ready for its conveyance to Leeds by the next day. Rossetti expresses his approval of Heaton's plans to secure some mounted drawings by Alphonse Legros.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Bethlehem Gate; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Legros, Alphonse, 1837-1911; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 May 16; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.65)
  Rossetti tells Heaton he does not believe that Dante's dream would have been damaged in transportation and says that the delay in sending it was a result of the necessity of copying it and the difficulties in mounting it. Rossetti has begun copying the pencil drawing in red chalk which he thinks will be an improvement. He believes the piece and Bethlehem Gate will leave for Leeds on Thursday (the 19th). He tells Heaton that she can visit him on Thursday at 11am or at 5pm to see the chalk drawing.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Bethlehem Gate; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 June 28; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.86)
  Rossetti asks Heaton to visit him on Friday at 4 pm or after, or on Saturday at 12 noon or 1 pm to see her Sir Galahad drawing. He reasserts the price of the piece as 100 guineas and asks Heaton if he could have £55 when she visits as he is "obliged to go out of town on Saturday for a day of two, to avoid a summons on the Grand Jury (!)" Rossetti says his Joan of Arc is nearly complete and hopes that Heaton will enjoy the Sir Galahad which he thinks is becoming one of his best works. Rossetti expects Heaton for dinner on Thursday at his mother's, alongside Mr. and Mrs. Aldam Heaton. Rossetti has visited the "smelling little shops" and has "got one on approval to show [Heaton]." Rossetti proclaims that the photograph of Dante's dream is "a bogie with a vengeance," bemoaning its colours and the fact that one side of the photo is darker than the other, "which must be owing to bungling."
  Photography; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 July 1; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 11 x 19 cm, folded to 11 x 10 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.91)
  "I think it would have been as well if I had not mentioned particulars respecting the 2 commissions I was speaking of last night, or the names of the givers thereof, so will you kindly consider it for your private ear. You may, I think, probably meet the Aldam Heatons here on Saturday morning though I am not sure; and this chiefly cause me to write as I remember Mr. H. mentioning to me that I might as well keep my counsel on the point."
  Heaton, Aldam; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 July 2; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.94)
  Rossetti is concerned that Heaton believes her commissioned drawing to be small in relation to its price. Rossetti tells her that Mr. Dunlop recently paid 100 guineas each for two of his drawings, a price paid by others to Mr. Gambart (a dealer) for similar ones. Rossetti cites another instance in which a drawing smaller than the Sir Galahad had fetched 120 guineas and says that 100 guineas has become his standard rate for private commissions. He suggests that if Heaton looks at Dunlop's drawings, she will see that she is receiving more work for the same price. Despite Heaton's kind words about the Sir Galahad, Rossetti is writing to her "to remove any impression, however slight, that [he is] treating so faithful a friend and purchaser as [Heaton] at any disadvantage compared with others."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Gambart, Ernest, 1814-1902; Dunlop, Walter, active 1857-1885; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 July 12; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.103)
  "The Sir Galahad will be finished tomorrow. What do you like me to do with it. Would it suit you to come to see it Saturday at 12 or 1?"
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 July 18; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.107)
  Rossetti hopes it will be possible to set Heaton's mind at rest about "the lily" but he is not sure he will be able to. Rossetti asks Heaton if she would prefer a drawing "of "the small figure kind to the Joan of Arc ," which he would be happy to substitute for it, provided Heaton lets him know if she would like one as soon as possible. The price of the drawing would be 100 guineas. Rossetti tells Heaton that his mother is sitting for him the following day and asked if Heaton would like to join them. He tells her to come at any time of the day, that they will dine at 7 pm and that his sister, Maria and Dr. and Mrs. Hesinam will be coming in the evening.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 October 3; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.135)
  Rossetti tells Heaton that he will be sending the Joan of Arc by the end of the week. Rossetti hopes Heaton will like it "as everyone says it is one of my best things. I myself (entre nous) consider it superior in expression and colour to the oil picture." Rossetti has told Mr. Rose that Heaton would show him her pictures if she visited her. Rossetti tells Heaton that he is going to Paris on the advice of his doctor and asks if he can "fetch, carry or bring anything" for her. He ends by saying that the Sir Galahad will be sent to Heaton, along with the Joan of Arc.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Rose, James Anderson, 1819-1890; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 October 8; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.137)
  Rossetti admits that the Joan of Arc is taking longer than expected but he promises to send it the next Tuesday or Wednesday. Rossetti asks if, upon receipt of the letter, she sends the £105 the work costs and specifies that the best way to send the money would be by two Bank of England notes (for £100 and £5) by registered letter. Rossetti thinks that Heaton will like the Joan of Arc which "pleases [Rossetti] rather beyond usually." He promises to send his autographs and photography with the Sir Galahad.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 October 16; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.138)
  Rossetti hopes that Heaton has received the autographs and photographs he gave to Christina Rossetti to pass on to Heaton. He tells Heaton that Lady Ashburton was delighted with the Joan of Arc and Sir Galahad and was disappointed she could not have them. Rossetti says that he fears that he would "seem shabby" if he asks Heaton to purchase the work's frame and so he has ordered a suitable frame to include with the work.